<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
    xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
    xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0/" article-type="research-article"
    dtd-version="1.3" xml:lang="en">
    <front>
        <journal-meta>
            <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">default</journal-id>
            <journal-title-group>
                <journal-title>default</journal-title>
                <abbrev-journal-title>default</abbrev-journal-title>
            </journal-title-group>
            <issn publication-format="electronic" pub-type="epub">1234-232</issn>
            <issn publication-format="print" pub-type="ppub">123-12</issn>
            <publisher>
                <publisher-name>default</publisher-name>
            </publisher>
        </journal-meta>
        <article-meta>
            <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">default123</article-id>
            <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/default123</article-id>
            <title-group>
                <article-title>Title: <italic>Opening science to society: how to progress societal
                    engagement into (open) science policies</italic></article-title>
            </title-group>
            <contrib-group content-type="author">
                <contrib contrib-type="author"><name data-ref="Corresponding Author"
                        rid="9d2b8936-38dd-4946-a514-b263ec8bb517"><surname>Wehn</surname>, <given-name>
                    U.</given-name><sup>
                            <xref ref-type="aff" sub-type="1"
                                rid="9d2b8936-38dd-4946-a514-b263ec8bb517">1</xref>
                        </sup></name><xref
                        ref-type="aff" sub-type="1" data-ref="corresponding">*</xref>, <name
                        rid="aa118c83-bc90-459c-ac01-11808bdf844d"><surname>Ajates</surname>, <given-name>
                    R.</given-name><sup>
                            <xref ref-type="aff" sub-type="2"
                                rid="aa118c83-bc90-459c-ac01-11808bdf844d">2</xref>
                        </sup></name>
                    , <name rid="f14bc274-207d-41c9-911d-e8ac29a7c693"><surname>Mandeville</surname>
                    , <given-name>C.</given-name><sup>
                            <xref ref-type="aff" sub-type="3"
                                rid="f14bc274-207d-41c9-911d-e8ac29a7c693">3</xref>
                        </sup></name>
                    , <name rid="9d2b8936-38dd-4946-a514-b263ec8bb517"><surname>Somerwill</surname>, <given-name>
                    L.</given-name><sup>
                            <xref ref-type="aff" sub-type="4"
                                rid="9d2b8936-38dd-4946-a514-b263ec8bb517">1</xref>
                        </sup></name>
                    , <name rid="0962e956-db3e-4a74-83f3-cb54aed84201"><surname>Kragh</surname>, <given-name>
                    G.</given-name><sup>
                            <xref ref-type="aff" sub-type="5"
                                rid="0962e956-db3e-4a74-83f3-cb54aed84201">4</xref>
                        </sup></name>
                    , <name rid="39785930-1f5f-4066-a4e2-11c53ec502fa"><surname>Haklay</surname>, <given-name>
                    M<sup>.</sup></given-name><sup>
                            <xref ref-type="aff" sub-type="6"
                                rid="39785930-1f5f-4066-a4e2-11c53ec502fa">5</xref>
                        </sup></name>
                </contrib>
                <aff id="9d2b8936-38dd-4946-a514-b263ec8bb517" data-ref="Corresponding Affiliation"><sup>
                        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="9d2b8936-38dd-4946-a514-b263ec8bb517">1</xref>
                    </sup> <institution>IHE
                    Delft Institute for Water Education</institution>, Westvest 7, 2601DA Delft, <country>The
                    Netherlands</country></aff>
                <aff id="aa118c83-bc90-459c-ac01-11808bdf844d"><sup>
                        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="aa118c83-bc90-459c-ac01-11808bdf844d">2</xref>
                    </sup>
                    Raquel: <institution>Universidad Nacional de Educaci&#x00F3;n a Distancia</institution>,
                    Calle Obispo Trejo, n&#x00BA;2, 28040 (Madrid), <country>Spain</country>
                    &#x0026; University of Dundee, United Kingdom</aff>
                <aff id="f14bc274-207d-41c9-911d-e8ac29a7c693"><sup>
                        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="f14bc274-207d-41c9-911d-e8ac29a7c693">3</xref>
                    </sup>
                    Centre for Biodiversity Dynamics, <institution content-type="department">Department
                    of Natural History</institution>, <institution>Norwegian University of Science
                    and Technology</institution>, H&#x00F8;gskoleringen 1, 7034 Trondheim, <country>
                    Norway</country></aff>
                <aff id="0962e956-db3e-4a74-83f3-cb54aed84201"><sup>
                        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="0962e956-db3e-4a74-83f3-cb54aed84201">4 </xref>
                    </sup><institution
                        content-type="department">Centre for Science Studies</institution>, <institution>Aarhus
                    University</institution>, Ny Munkegade 118, 8000 Aarhus C, <country>Denmark</country></aff>
                <aff id="39785930-1f5f-4066-a4e2-11c53ec502fa"><sup>
                        <xref ref-type="aff" rid="39785930-1f5f-4066-a4e2-11c53ec502fa">5</xref>
                    </sup> <institution
                        content-type="department">Department of Geography</institution>, <institution>University
                    College London</institution>, Gower Street, London WC1E 6BT, <country>United
                    Kingdom</country>
                </aff>
            </contrib-group>
            <author-notes>
                <corresp id="59037959-dab2-4990-9d1d-17384529f2d5"><xref ref-type="aff"
                        rid="59037959-dab2-4990-9d1d-17384529f2d5">*</xref>corresponding author: <email>
                    u.wehn@un-ihe.org</email></corresp>
            </author-notes>
            <pub-date pub-type="ppub" />
            <abstract>
                <title>Abstract:</title>
                <p>A broad understanding of the aims and objectives of the international open
                    science movement was recently adopted with the 2021 UNESCO Recommendation on
                    Open Science, expanding the focus of open science to include scientific
                    knowledge, infrastructures, knowledge systems, and the open engagement of
                    societal actors. In response, recent discussions on science policy practice are
                    shifting to the implementation of open science via national policy. While policy
                    instruments to support some aspects of open science are well-studied, guidance
                    on the emerging &#x2018;social&#x2019; aspects of open science has lagged,
                    prompting UNESCO to generate guidance. In this paper, authors of a UNESCO Open
                    Science Toolkit guidance document on &#x201C;Engaging societal actors in Open
                    Science&#x201D; synthesise the scholarly underpinnings behind the guidance
                    document&#x2019;s recommendations. This work draws upon a targeted search from
                    academic, policy, and grey literature in the fields of open
                    &#x00A0;&#x00A0;&#x00A0;&#x00A0;&#x00A0;science and community engagement, with a
                    special focus on citizen science, to derive guidance on how to overcome barriers
                    for the uptake of societal engagement approaches. The results present building
                    blocks of what an enabling environment for the open engagement of societal
                    actors could look like, identifying key considerations and reflecting on
                    opportunities and challenges for progressing and evaluating sound open
                    engagement of societal actors into regional &#x0026; national (open) science
                    policies.</p>
            </abstract>
            <kwd-group>
                <kwd>citizen science</kwd>
                <kwd>open science</kwd>
                <kwd>open data</kwd>
                <kwd>open access</kwd>
                <kwd>policy recommendations</kwd>
                <kwd>societal engagement</kwd>
            </kwd-group>
        </article-meta>
    </front>
    <body>
        <sec id="s1">
            <sec id="s1.1">
                <p>&#x00A0;<bold>Authors</bold>: </p>
            </sec>
        </sec>
        <sec id="s2">
            <title>1 &#x2013; Introduction</title>
            <p>While policy instruments to support some aspects of open science are available -
                including open access and open data, guidance on the emerging &#x2018;social&#x2019;
                aspects of open science has lagged. The 2021 UNESCO Recommendation on Open
                Science&#x2019;s identification of &#x201C;Open engagement of societal
                actors&#x201D; as a pillar of open science has prompted increased focus on social
                aspects of open science, resulting in the development of a specific guide in the
                UNESCO Open Science Toolkit, summarising regional and national policy
                recommendations to support the open engagement of societal actors. Here, authors of
                this guide on engagement of societal actors in open science report, expand, and
                reflect upon the scholarly underpinnings behind the guidance document&#x2019;s
                recommendations. Our general aim is to support the application of the guide by
                different stakeholder groups. The guide was addressed to policy makers and policy
                professionals who are less familiar with the field, to benefit from understanding
                the place of citizen science within the wider field of Open Science. Through this
                paper, researchers and practitioners can access the additional details that clarify
                the underlying work that led to the guide, with the view of informing their open
                science practice, and for the OS guidance document to be built upon, critically
                evaluated, and improved over time. In 2019, the 193 UNESCO Member States tasked the
                organisation with the development of an international standard-setting instrument on
                Open Science in the form of a UNESCO Recommendation. </p>
            <p>The UNESCO Recommendation on Open Science was adopted by the General Conference of
                UNESCO at its 41st session, in November 2021,</p>
            <p>
                <italic>&#x201C;Noting the transformative potential of open science for reducing the
                    existing inequalities in STI [i.e. science, technology &#x0026; innovation;
                    added] and accelerating progress towards the implementation of the 2030 Agenda
                    and the achievement of the Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs) and
                    beyond.&#x201D;</italic>
            </p>
            <p><italic>&#x201C;Considering that more open, transparent, collaborative and inclusive
                scientific practices, coupled with more accessible and verifiable scientific
                knowledge subject to scrutiny and critique, is a more efficient enterprise that
                improves the quality, reproducibility and impact of science, and thereby the
                reliability of the evidence needed for robust decision-making and policy and
                increased trust in science.&#x201D;</italic> [p.2] </p>
            <p>"Open Science" is an umbrella concept, which includes a range of "open" labels of
                research practices, such as Open Source Software, Open Access to publications, Open
                Educational Resources, Open Data, as well as opening the process of scientific
                knowledge production to other actors, or "citizen science" in its dual value of
                science produced by citizens - through the collection of data and involvement in
                other steps of the scientific method - and science made for citizens, or scientific
                communication.</p>
            <p>Open science emerged in the late 2000s, as a solution to address recognised issues in
                scientific practices (such as the difficulties in accessing scientific papers) and
                by taking advantage of emerging web technologies (see for example<xref
                    ref-type="bibr" sub-type="authorYear" rid="RR67">, Nielsen 2011<xref
                        ref-type="bibr" sub-type="authorYear" rid="R9">, Boulton et al., 2012).</xref></xref>
                Its original formation highlighted open scientific data as a core principle, joined
                by open access publication and open source scientific software, as well as openness
                to the public in terms of their engagement in scientific practice. In practice, most
                attention was paid to the aspects that are at the core of the concerns of scientists
                such as Open Access and Open Data. Since then, the concept evolved, with an adoption
                of it by the European Commission as a central part of research policy <xref
                    ref-type="bibr" sub-type="authorYear" rid="RR12">(Burgelman et al. 2019),</xref>
                with eight areas of activity: rewards and incentives, indicators and next-generation
                metrics, future of scholarship, European Open Science Cloud (EOSC), FAIR data,
                research integrity, skills and education, and citizen science (European Commission,
                Directorate-General for Research and Innovation, Mendez<xref ref-type="bibr"
                    sub-type="authorYear" rid="RR26">, Lawrence, 2020).</xref> Eventually, global
                awareness, attention and some form of consensus converged and materialised in the
                form of the UNESCO Recommendation on Open Science. This Recommendation was motivated
                by the need to change &#x2018;science as usual&#x2019; in order to achieve the
                Sustainable Development Goals (SDGs) and was adopted by all Member States in
                November 2021. </p>
        </sec>
    </body>
</article>